all right so as you can see today we
don't have Yong Yong is somewhere else
having fun
hyeyeon okay so today's that we have our
own de facto he's a research scientist
at Facebook working mostly on
optimization
he's been there for the past three years
and before he was a data scientist at
Amita and then a student at the
Australian National University so why
don't we give a round of applause to the
our speaker today I'll be talking about
optimization and if we have time at the
end the death of optimization so these
are the topics I will be covering today
now optimization is at the heart of
machine learning and some of the things
are going to be talking about today will
be used every day in your role
potentially as an applied scientist or
even as a research scientist or a data
scientist and I'm gonna focus on the
application of these methods
particularly rather than the theory
behind them part of the reason for this
is that we don't fully understand all of
these methods so for me to come up here
and say this is why it works I would be
oversimplifying things but what I can
tell you is how to use them how we know
that they work in certain situations and
what the best method may be to use to
train your neural network and to
introduce you to the topic of
optimization I need to start with the
worst method in the world gradient
descent and I'll explain in a minute why
it's the worst method but to begin with
we're going to use the most generic
formulation of optimization now the
problems you're going to be considering
will have more structure than this but
it's very useful useful notationally to
start this way so we talked about a
function f now we're trying to prove
properties of our optimizer will assume
additional structure on f but in
practice the structure in our neural
networks essentially obey no of the
assumptions
none of the assumptions people make in
practice
I'm just gonna start with the generic F
and we'll assume it's continuous and
differentiable even though we're already
getting into the realm of incorrect
assumptions since the neural networks
most people are using in practice these
days are not differentiable instead you
have a equivalent sub differential which
you can essentially plug into all these
formulas and if you cross your fingers
there's no theory to support this it
should work so the method of gradient
descent is shown here it's an iterative
method so you start at a point k equals
zero and at each step you update your
point and here we're going to use W to
represent our current iterate either it
being the standard nomenclature for the
point for your neural network this w
will be some large collection of weights
one weight tensor per layer but notation
we we kind of squash the whole thing
down to a single vector and you can
imagine just doing that literally by
reshaping all your vectors to all your
tensors two vectors and just concatenate
them together and this method is
remarkably simple all we do is we follow
the direction of the negative gradient
and the rationale for this it's pretty
simple so let me give you a diagram and
maybe this will help explain exactly why
following the negative gradient
direction is a good idea so we don't
know enough about our function to do
better this is a high level idea when
we're optimizing a function we look at
the landscape the optimization landscape
locally so by optimization landscape I
mean the domain of all possible weights
of our network now we don't know what's
going to happen if we use any particular
weights on your network we don't know if
it'll be better at the task we're trying
to train it to or worse but we do know
locally is the point that are currently
ad and the gradient and this gradient
provides some information about a
direction which we can travel in that
may improve the performance of our
network or in this case reduce the value
of our function were minimizing here in
this set up this general setup
minimizing a function is essentially
training in your network so minimizing
the loss will give you the best
performance on your classification task
or whatever you're trying to do and
because we only look at the world
locally here this gradient is basically
the best information we have and you can
think of this as descending a valley
where you start somewhere horrible some
pinkie part of the landscape the top of
a mountain for instance and you travel
down from there and at each point you
follow the direction near you that has
the most sorry the steepest descent and
in fact the go the method of grading %
is sometimes called the method of
steepest descent and this direction will
change as you move in the space now if
you move locally by only an
infinitesimal amount assuming this
smoothness that I mentioned before which
is actually not true in practice but
we'll get to that assuming the
smoothness this small step will only
change the gradient a small amount so
the direction you're traveling in is at
least a good direction when you take
small steps and we essentially just
follow this path taking as larger steps
as we can
traversing the landscape until we reach
the valley at the bottom which is the
minimizer our function now there's a
little bit more we can say for some
problem classes and I'm going to use the
most simplistic problem class we can
just because it's the only thing that I
can really do any mathematics for on one
slide so bear with me
this class is quadratics so for a
quadratic optimization problem we
actually know quite a bit just based off
the gradient so firstly a gradient cuts
off an entire half of a space and now
illustrate this here with this green
line so we're at that point there where
the line starts near the Green Line we
know the solution cannot be in the rest
of the space and this is not true from
your networks but it's still a genuinely
a good guideline that we want to follow
the direction of negative gradient there
could be better solutions elsewhere in
the space but finding them is is much
harder than just trying to find the best
solution near to where we are so that's
what we do we trying to find the best
solution near to where we are you could
imagine this being the surface of the
earth where there are many hills and
valleys and we can't hope to know
something about a mountain on the other
side of the planet but we can certainly
look for the valley directly beneath the
mountain where we currently are
in fact you can think of these functions
here as being represented with these
topographic maps this is the same as
topographic maps you use that you may be
familiar with from from the planet Earth
where mountains are shown by these rings
now here the rings are representing
descent so this is the bottom of the
valley we're showing here not the top of
a hill at the center there so yes our
gradient knocks off a whole half of the
possible space now it's very reasonable
then to go in the direction find this
negative gradient because it's kind of
orthogonal to this line that cuts off
after space and you can see that I've
got the indication of orthogonal you
there the little la square so the
properties of gradient to spend a
gradient descent depend greatly on the
structure of the problem for these
quadratic problems it's actually
relatively simple to characterize what
will happen so I'm going to give you a
little bit of an overview here and I'll
spend a few minutes on this because it's
quite interesting and I'm hoping that
those of you with some background in
linear algebra can follow this
derivation but we're going to consider a
quadratic optimization problem
now the problem stated in the gray box
at the top you can see that this is a
quadratic where a is a positive definite
matrix we can handle broader classes of
Quadra quadratics and this potentially
but the analysis is most simple in the
positive definite case and the grating
of that function is very simple of
course as a w- b and u the solution of
this problem has a closed form in the
case of quadratics it's as inverse of a
times B now what we do is we take the
steps they're shown in the green box and
we just plug it into the distance from
solution so this wk minus 1 minus W star
is a distance from solution so we want
to see how this changes over time and
the idea is that if we're moving closer
to the solution over time the method is
converging so we start with that
distance from solution to be plug in the
value of the update now with a little
bit of rearranging we can pull
the terms we can group the terms
together and we can write B as a inverse
so we can pull or we can pull the W star
inside the inside the brackets there and
then we get this expression where it's
matrix times the previous distance to
the solution matrix times previous
distance solution now we don't know
anything about which directions this
quadratic it varies most extremely in
but we can just not bound this very
simply by taking the product of the
matrix as norm and the distance to the
solution here this norm at the bottom so
that's the bottom line now now when
you're considering matrix norms it's
pretty straightforward to see that
you're going to have an expression where
the eigen values of this matrix are
going to be 1 minus mu gamma or 1 minus
L gamma now the way I get this is I just
look at what are the extreme eigen
values of a which we call them mu and L
and by plugging these into the
expression we can see what the extreme
eigen values will be of this combined
matrix I minus gamma a and you have this
absolute value here now you can optimize
this and get an optimal learning rate
for the quadratics
but that optimal learning rate is not
robust in practice you probably don't
want to use that so a simpler value you
can use is 1 over L ll being the largest
eigen value and this gives you this
convergence rate of 1 minus mu L
reduction in distance to solution every
step do we have any questions here I
know it's a little dense
yes yes it's it's a substitution from in
that gray box do you see the bottom line
on the gray box yeah that's that's just
a by definition we can solve the
gradient so by taking the gradient to
zero if you see in that second line in
the box
taking the gradient to zero this so
replaced our gradient with zero and
rearranging you get the closed form
solution to the problem here so the
problem with using that closed form
solution in practice is we have to
invert a matrix and by using gradient
descent we can solve this problem by
only doing matrix multiplications
instead I'm not that I would suggest you
actually use this technique to solve the
matrix as I mentioned before it's the
worst method in the world and the
convergence rate of this method is
controlled by this new overall quantity
now these are standard notations so
we're going from linear algebra where
you talk about the min and Max eigen
value to the notation typically used in
the field of optimization moving
smallest eigen value L being largest
eigen value and this mu over L is the
inverse of the condition number
condition number being L over Mir this
gives you a broad characterization of
how quickly optimization methods will
work on this problem and this these
military terms they don't exist for
neural networks only in the very
simplest situations do we have L exists
and we essentially never have mu
existing nevertheless we want to talk
about network networks being polar
conditioned and well conditioned and
poorly conditioned would typically be
some approximation to L is very large
and well conditioned maybe L is very
close to one so the step size we can
select in one summer training depends
very heavily on these constants so let
me give you a little bit of an intuition
for step sizes and this is very
important in practice I myself find a
lot of my time is spent treating
learning rates and I'm sure you'll be
involved in similar procedure so we have
a couple of situations that can occur if
we use a learning rate that's too low
we'll find that we make steady progress
towards the solution here we're
minimizing a little 1d quadratic and by
steady progress I mean that every
iteration the gradient stays in buffer
the same direction and you make similar
progress as you approach the solution
this is slower than it is possible so
what you would ideally want to do is go
straight to the solution for a quadratic
especially a 1d one like this that's
going to be pretty straightforward
there's going to be an exact step size
that'll get you all the way to solution
but more generally you can't do that
and what you typically want to use is
actually a step size a bit above that
optimal and this is for a number of
reasons it tends to be quicker in
practice we have to be very very careful
because you get divergence and the term
divergence means that the iterates will
get further away than from the solution
instead of closer this will typically
happen if you use two larger learning
rate unfortunately for us we want to use
learning rates as large as possible to
get as quick learning as possible so
we're always at the edge of divergence
in fact it's very rare that you'll see
that the gradients follow this nice
trajectory where they all point the same
direction until you kind of reach the
solution what almost always happens in
practice especially with gradient
descent invariants is that you observe
this zigzagging behavior now we can't
actually see zigzagging in million
dimensional spaces that we train your
networks in but it's very evident in
these 2d plots of a quadratic so here
I'm showing the level sets you can see
the numbers or the function value
indicated there on the level sets and
when we use a learning rate that is good
not optimal but good we get pretty close
to that blue dot the solution are for
the 10 steps when we use a learning rate
that seems nicer in that it's not
oscillating it's well-behaved when we
use such a learning rate we actually end
up quite a bit further away from the
solution so it's a fact of life that we
have to deal with these learning rates
that are stressfully high it's kind of
like a race right you know no one wins a
a race by driving safely so our network
training should be very comparable to
that so the core topic we want to talk
about is actually it stochastic
optimization and this is the method that
we will be using every day for training
neural networks in practice so it's de
casting optimization is actually not so
different what we're gonna do is we're
going to replace the gradients in our
gradient descent step with a stochastic
approximation to the gradient now in a
neural network we can be a bit more
precise here by stochastic approximation
what we mean is the gradient of the loss
for a single data point single instance
you might want to call it so I've got
that in the notation here this function
L is the loss of one day the point here
the data point is indexed by AI and we
would write this typically in the
optimization literature as the function
fi and I'm going to use this notation
but you should imagine fi as being the
loss for a single instance I and here
I'm using supervised learning setup
where we have data points I labels Y I
so they points X I labels Y I the full
loss for a function is shown at the top
there it's a sum of all these F is now
let me give you a bit more explanation
for what we're doing here we're placing
this through gradient with a stochastic
gradient this is a Luisi approximation
and this is how it's often explained in
the stochastic optimization setup so we
have this function the gradient and in
our setup it's expected value is equal
to the full gradient so you can think of
a stochastic gradient descent step as
being a full gradient step in
expectation now this is not actually the
best way to view it because there's a
lot more going on than that it's not
just gradient descent with noise so let
me give you a little bit more detail but
first I let anybody ask any questions I
have here before I move on yes
mm-hmm yeah I could talk a bit more
about that but yes so you're right so
using your entire dataset to calculate a
gradient is here what I mean by gradient
descent we also call that full batch
gradient descent just to be clear now in
machine learning we virtually always use
mini batches so people may use the name
gradient descent or something when
they're really talking about stochastic
gradient descent and what you mentioned
is absolutely true so there are some
difficulties of training neural networks
using very large batch sizes and this is
understood to some degree and I'll
actually explain that on the very next
slide so let me let me get to to your
point first
so the point the answer to your question
is actually the third point here the
noise in stochastic gradient descent
induces this phenomena known as
annealing and the diagram directly to
the right of it illustrates this
phenomena so your network training
landscapes have a bumpy structure to
them where there are lots of small
minima that are not good minima that
appear on the path to the good minima so
the theory that a lot of people
subscribe to is that SGD in particular
the noise induced in the gradient
actually helps the optimizer to jump
over these bad minima and the theory is
that these bad minima are quite small in
the space and so they're easy to jump
over we're good minima that results in
good performance around your own network
are larger and harder to skip so does
this answer your question yes so besides
that annealing point of view there's
there's actually a few other reasons so
we have a lot of redundancy in the
information we get from each terms
gradient and using stochastic gradient
lets us exploit this redundancy in a lot
of situations the gradient computed on a
few hundred examples is almost as good
as a gradient computed on the full data
set and often thousands of times cheaper
depending on your problem so it's it's
hard to come up with a compelling reason
to use gradient descent given the
success of stochastic gradient descent
and this is part of the reason why
disgusted gradient said is one of the
best misses we have but gradient descent
is one of the worst and in fact early
stages the correlation is remarkable
this disgusted gradient can be
correlated up to a coefficient of 0.999
correlation coefficient to the true
gradient at those early steps of
optimization so I want to briefly talk
about a something you need to know about
I think Jana has already mentioned this
briefly but in practice we don't use
individual instances in stochastic
gradient descent how we use mini batches
of instances so I'm just using some
notation here but everybody uses
different notation for mini batching so
you shouldn't get too attached to the
notation but essentially at every step
you have some batch here I'm going to
call it B an index with I for step and
you basically use the average of the
gradients over this mini batch which is
a subset of your data rather than a
single instance or the full full batch
now almost everybody will use this mini
batch selected uniformly at random
some people use with replacement
sampling and some people use without
with replacement sampling but the
differences are not important for this
purposes you can use either and there's
a lot of advantages to mini batching so
there's actually some good impelling
theoretical reasons to not be any batch
but the practical reasons are
overwhelming part of these practical
reasons are computational we make
ammonia may utilize our hardware say at
1% efficiency when training some of the
network's we use if we try and use
single instances and we get the most
efficient utilization of the hardware
with batch sizes often in the hundreds
if you're training on the typical
imagenet data set for in for instance
you don't use batch sizes less than
about 64 to get good efficiency maybe
can go down to 32 but another important
application is distributed training and
this is really becoming a big thing so
as was mentioned before people were
recently able to Train imagenet days
said that normally takes two days to
train and not so long ago it took
in a week to train in only one hour and
the way they did that was using very
large mini batches and along with using
large many batches there are some tricks
that you need to use to get it to work
it's probably not something that you
would cover an introductory lecture so I
encourage you to check out that paper if
you're interested it's imagenet in one
hour
leaves face book authors I can't recall
the first author at the moment as a side
note there are some situations where you
need to do full batch optimization do
not use gradient descent in that
situation I can't emphasize it enough to
not use gradient ascent ever if you have
full batch data by far the most
effective method that is kind of
plug-and-play you don't to think about
it is known as l-bfgs it's accumulation
of 50 years of optimization research and
it works really well
torch's implementation is pretty good
but the SyFy implementation causes some
filtering code that was written 15 years
ago that is pretty much bulletproof so
because they were those so that's a good
question
classically you do need to use the full
data set
now pipe torches implementation actually
supports using mini battery now this is
somewhat of a gray area in that there's
really no theory to support the use of
this and it may work well for your
problem or it may not so it could be
worth trying I mean you want to use your
whole data set for each gradient
evaluation or probably more likely since
it's very rarely you want to do that
probably more likely you're solving some
other optimization problem that isn't
isn't training in your network but maybe
some ancillary problem related and you
need to solve an optimization problem
without this data point structure that
doesn't summer isn't a sum of data
points yeah hopefully it was another
question yep oh yes the question was
young recommended we used mini batches
equal to the size of the number of
classes we have in our data set why is
that reasonable that was the question
the answer is that we want any vectors
to be representative of the full data
set and typically each class is quite
distinct from the other classes in its
properties so about using a mini batch
that contains on average
one instance from each class in fact we
can enforce that explicitly although
it's not necessary
by having an approximately equal to that
size we can assume it has the kind of
structure of a food gradient so you
capture a lot of the correlations in the
data you see with the full gradient and
it's a good guide especially if you're
using training on CPU where you're not
constrained too much by hardware
efficiency here when training on energy
on a CPU batch size is not critical for
hardware utilization it's problem
dependent I would always recommend mini
batching I don't think it's worth trying
size one as a starting point if you try
to eke out small gains maybe that's
worth exploring yes there was another
question so in the annealing example so
the question was why is the lost
landscape so wobbly and this is this is
actually something that is very a very
realistic depiction of actual law slams
codes for neural networks they're
incredibly in the sense that they have a
lot of hills and valleys and this is
something that is actively researched
now what we can say for instance is that
there is a very large number of good
minima and and so hills and valleys we
know this because your networks have
this combinatorial aspect to them you
can reaper ammeter eyes a neural network
by shifting all the weights around and
you can get in your work you'll know if
it outputs exactly the same output for
whatever task you're looking at with all
these weights moved around and that
correspondence essentially to a
different location in parameter space so
given that there's an exponential number
of these possible ways of rearranging
the weights to get the same network
you're going to end up with the space
that's incredibly spiky exponential
number of these spikes now the reason
why these these local minima appear that
is something that is still active
research so I'm not sure I can give you
a great answer there but they're
definitely observed in practice and what
I can say is they appear to be less of a
problem we've very
like close to state-of-the-art networks
so these local minima were considered
big problems 15 years ago but so much at
the moment people essentially never hit
them in practice when using kind of
recommended parameters and things like
that when you use very large batches you
can run into these problems it's not
even clear that the the poor performance
when using large batches is even
attributable to these larger minima to
these local minima so this is yes to
ongoing research yes the problem is you
can't really see this local structure
because we're in this million
dimensional space it's not a good way to
see it so yeah I don't know if people
might have explored that already I'm not
familiar with papers on that but I bet
someone has looked at it so you might
want to google that yeah so a lot of the
advances in neural network design have
actually been in reducing this bumpiness
in a lot of ways so this is part of the
reason why it's not considered a huge
problem anymore whether it was it was
considered a big problem in the past
there's any other questions yes so it's
it is hard to see but there are certain
things you can do that we make the the
peaks and valleys smaller certainly and
by rescaling some parts the neural
network you can amplify certain
directions the curvature in certain
directions can be stretched and squashed
the particular innovation residual
connections that were mentioned they're
very easy to see that they smooth out
the the loss in fact you can kind of
draw two line between two points in the
space and you can see what happens along
that line that's really the best way we
have a visualizing million dimensional
spaces so I turn him into one dimension
and you can see that it's that it's a
much nicer between these two points
whatever two points you choose when
using these residual connections I'll be
talking all about dodging or later in
the lecture so yeah if hopefully I'll
answer that question without you having
to ask it again but we'll see
thanks any other questions yes so l-bfgs
excellent method it's it's kind of a
constellation of optimization
researchers that we still use SGD a
method invented in the 60s or earlier is
still state of the art but there has
been some innovation in fact only a
couple years later but there was some
innovation since the invention of sed
and one of these innovations is
and I'll talk about another later so
momentum it's a trick
that you should pretty much always be
using when you're using stochastic
gradient descent it's worth be going
into this in a little bit of detail
you'll often be tuning the momentum
parameter and your network and it's
useful to understand what it's actually
doing when you're tuning up so part of
the problem with momentum it's very
misunderstood and this can be explained
by the fact that there's actually three
different ways of writing momentum that
look completely different but turn out
to be equivalent I'm only going to
present two of these ways because the
third way is not as well known but is
actually in my opinion the correct way
to view it I don't talk about my
research here so we'll talk about how
it's actually implemented in the
packages you'll be using and this first
form here is what's actually implemented
in Python and other software that you'll
be using here we maintain two variables
now you'll see lots of papers using
different notation here P is the
notation used in physics for momentum
and it's very common to use that also as
the momentum variable when talking about
sed with momentum so I'll be following
that convention so instead of having a
single iterate we now have to Eretz P
and W and at every step we update both
and this is quite a simple update so the
P update involves adding to the old P
and instead of adding exactly to the old
P we kind of damp the old P we reduce it
by multiplying it by a constant that's
worse than one so reduce the old P and
here I'm using beta hat as the constant
there so that would probably be 0.9 in
practice a small amount of damping and
we add to that the new gradient so P is
kind of this accumulated gradient buffer
you can think of where new gradients
come in at full value and past gradients
are reduced at each step by a certain
factor usually 0.9 which used to reduce
reduced so the buffer tends to be a some
sort of running sum of gradients and
it's basically we just modify this to
custer gradient two-step descent step by
using this P instead of the negative
gradient instead of the gradient sorry
using P instead of the
in the update since the two line formula
it may be better to understand this by
the second form that I put below this is
equivalent you've got a map the beta
with a small transformation so it's not
exactly the same beta between the two
methods but it's practically the same
for in practice so these are essentially
the same up to reap romanization and
this film I think is maybe clearer this
form is called the stochastic heavy ball
method and here our update still
includes the gradient but we're also
adding on a multiplied copy of the past
direction we traveled in now what does
this mean what are we actually doing
here so it's actually not too difficult
to visualize and I'm going to kind of
use a visualization from a distilled
publication you can see the dress at the
bottom there and I disagree with a lot
of what they talked about in that
document but I like the visualizations
so let's use had and I'll explain why I
disagreed some regards later but it's
quite simple so you can think of
momentum as the physical process and I
mention those of you have done
introductory physics courses would have
covered this so momentum is the property
of something to keep moving in the
direction that's currently moving in all
right if you're familiar with Newton's
laws things want to keep going in the
direction they're going and this is
momentum and when you do this mapping
the physics the gradient is kind of a
force that is pushing you're literate
which by this analogy is a heavy ball
it's pushing this heavy ball at each
point so rather than making dramatic
changes in the direction we travel at
every step which is shown in that left
diagram instead of making these dramatic
changes we're going to make kind of a
bit more modest changes so when we
realize we're going in the wrong
direction we kind of do a u-turn instead
of putting the hand brake on and
swinging around
it turns out in a lot of practical
problems this gives you a big
improvement so here you can see you're
getting much closer to the solution by
the end of it with much less oscillation
and you can see this oscillation so it's
kind of a fact of life if you're using
gradient descent type methods so here we
talk about momentum on top of gradient
descent in the visualization you're
gonna get this oscillation it's just a
property of gradient descent no way to
get rid of it without modifying the
method and we're meant to them to some
degree dampens this oscillation I've got
another visualization here which will
kind of give you an intuition for how
this beta parameter controls things now
the Department of these to be greater
than zero if it's equal to zero you
distr in gradient descent and it's gotta
be less than one otherwise the Met
everything blows up as you start
including past gradients with more and
more weight over times it's gotta be
between zero and one and typical values
range from you know small 0.25 up to
like 0.99 so in practice you can get
pretty close to one and what happens is
the smaller values they result in you're
changing direction quicker okay so in
this diagram you can see on the left
with the small beta you as soon as you
get close to the solution you kind of
change direction pretty rapidly and head
towards a solution when you use these
larger betas it takes longer for you to
make this dramatic turn you can think of
it as a car with a bad turning circle
takes you quite a long time to get
around that corner and head towards
solution now this may seem like a bad
thing but actually in practice this
significantly dampens the oscillations
that you get from gradient descent and
that's the nice property of it now in
terms of practice I can give you some
pretty clear guidance here you pretty
much always want to use momentum it's
pretty hard to find problems where it's
actually not beneficial to some degree
now part of the reason for this is it's
just an extra parameter now typically
when you take some method and just add
more parameters to it you can usually
find some value of that parameter that
makes us slightly better now that is
sometimes the case here but often these
improvements from using momentum are
actually quite substantial and
using a momentum value of point nine is
really a default value used in machine
learning quite often and often in some
situations 0.99 may be better so I would
recommend trying both values if you have
time otherwise just try point nine but I
have to do a warning the way momentum is
stated in this expression if you look at
it carefully when we increase the
momentum we kind of increase the step
size now it's not the step size of the
current gradient so the current gradient
is included in the step with the same
strengths but past gradients become
included in the step with a higher
strength when you increase momentum now
when you write momentum in other forms
this becomes a lot more obvious so this
firm kind of occludes that but what you
should generally do when you change
momentum you want to change it so that
you have your step size divided by one
minus beta is your new step size so if
your old step size was using a certain B
do you want to map it to that equation
then map it back to get the the new step
size now this may be very modest change
but if you're going from momentum 0.9 to
momentum 0.99 you may need to reduce
your learning rate by a factor of 10
approximately so just be wary of that
you can't expect to keep the same
learning rate and change the momentum
parameter at wallmart work now I want to
go into a bit of detail about why
momentum works is very misunderstood and
the explanation you'll see in that
Distilled post is acceleration and this
is certainly a contributor to the
performance of momentum now acceleration
is a topic yes if you've got a question
the question was is there a big
difference between using momentum and
using a mini batch of two and there is
so momentum has advantages in for when
using gradient descent as well as
stochastic gradient descent so in fact
this acceleration explanation were about
to use applies both in the stochastic
and non stochastic case so no matter
what batch size you're going to use the
benefits of momentum still are shown now
it also has benefits in the stochastic
case as well which I'll cover in a slide
or two so the answer is it's quite
distinct from batch size and you
shouldn't complete them
learn it like really you should be
changing your learning rate when you
change your bat size rather than
changing the momentum and for very large
batch sizes there's a clear relationship
between learning rate and batch size but
for small batch sizes it's not clear so
it's problem dependent any other
questions before I move on on momentum
yes yes it's it's just blow up so it's
actually in the in the in the physics
interpretation it's conservation of
momentum would be exactly equal to one
now that's not good because if you're in
a world with no friction then you drop a
heavy ball somewhere it's gonna keep
moving forever it's not good stuff so we
need some dampening and this is where
the physics interpretation breaks down
so you do need some damping now now you
can imagine if you use a larger value
than one those past gradients get
amplified every step so in fact the
first gradient you evaluate in your
network is not relevant information
content wise later in optimization but
if it used to be the larger than 1 it
would dominate the step that you're
using does that answer your question
yeah ok any other questions about
momentum before we move on they are for
a particular value of beta yes it's
strictly equivalent it's not very hard
to you should be able to do it in like
two lines if you try and do the
equivalence yourself no the bidders are
not quite the same but the the gamma is
the same that's why I use the same
notation for it oh yes so that's what I
mentioned yes so when you change beta
you want to scale your learning rate by
the learning rate divided by one over
beta so in this form I'm not sure if it
appears in this form it could be a
mistake but I think I'm okay here I
think it's not in this formula but yeah
what you definitely when you change beta
you need to change learning rate as well
to keep things balanced yeah
Oh either averaging form it's probably
not worth going over but you can think
of it as momentum is basically changing
the point that you evaluate the gradient
at in the standard firm you evaluate the
gradient at this W point in the inner
averaging form you take a running
average of the points you've been
evaluating the Grady Nutt and you
evaluate at that point so it's basically
instead of averaging gradients to
average points it's clear sense Jewell
yes yes so acceleration now this is
something you can spend the whole career
studying and it's it's somewhat poorly
understood now if you try and read
Nesterov original work on it now
Nesterov is kind of the grandfather of
modern optimization in practically half
the methods we use are named after him
to some degree which is can be confusing
at times and in the 80s he came up with
this formulation he didn't write it in
this form he wrote it in another form
which people realized a while later
could be written in this form and his
analysis is also very opaque and
originally written in Russian doesn't
help no for understanding unfortunately
those nice people the NSA translated all
of the Russian literature back then so
so we have access to them and it's
actually a very small modification of
the momentum step but I think that small
modification belittles what it's
actually doing it's really not the same
method at all what I can say is with
Nesterov Swimmer momentum if you very
carefully choose these constants you can
get what's known as accelerated
convergence now this doesn't apply in
your networks but for convex problems I
won't go into details of convexity but
some of you may know what that means
it's kind of a simple structure but
convex problems it's a radically
improved convergence rate from this
acceleration but only for very carefully
chosen constants and you really can't
choose these carefully ahead of time so
you've got to do quite a large search
over your parameters your hyper
parameters sorry to find the right
constants to get that acceleration what
I can say is this actually occurs for
quadratics when using regular momentum
and this is confused a lot of people
so you'll see a lot of people say that
momentum is an accelerated method it's
excited only for quadratics and even
then it's it's a little bit iffy I would
not recommend using it for quadratics
use conjugate gradients or some new
methods that have been developed over
the last few years and this is
definitely a contributing factor to our
momentum works so well in practice and
there's definitely some acceleration
going on but this acceleration is hard
to realize when you have stochastic
gradients now when you look at what
makes acceleration work noise really
kills it and it's it's hard to believe
that it's the main factor contributing
to the performance but it's certainly
there and the the still post I mentioned
attributes or the performance of
momentum to acceleration but I wouldn't
go that quite that far but it's
definitely a contributing factor but
probably the practical and provable
reason why acceleration why knows sorry
why momentum helps is noise smoothing
and this is very intuitive momentum
averages gradients in a sense we keep
this running buffer gradients that we
use as a step instead of individual
gradients this is kind of a form of
averaging and it turns out that when you
use s to D without momentum to prove
anything at all about it
you actually have to work with the
average of all the points you visited
you can get really weak bounds on the
last point that you ended up at but
really you've got to work with this
average of points and this is suboptimal
like we never want to actually take this
average in practice it's heavily
weighted with points that we visited a
long time ago which may be irrelevant
and in fact this averaging doesn't work
very well in practice for neural
networks it's really only important for
convex problems but nevertheless it's
necessary to analyze regular s2d and one
of the remarkable facts about momentum
is actually this averaging is no longer
theoretically necessary so essentially
momentum adds smoothing dream
optimization that makes it makes us so
the last point you visit is still a good
approximation to the solution with SGG
really you want to average a whole bunch
of last points you've seen in order to
get a good approximation to the solution
now let me illustrate that
here so this is this is a very typical
example of what happens when using STD
STD at the beginning you make great
progress the gradient is essentially
almost the same as the stochastic
gradient so first few steps you make
great progress towards solution but then
you end up in this ball now recall here
that's a valley that we're heading down
so this ball here is kind of the floor
of the valley and you kind of bounce
around in this floor and the most common
solution of this is if you reduce your
learning rate you'll bounce around
slower not exactly a great solution but
it's one way to handle it but when you
use s to deal with momentum you can kind
of smooth out this bouncing around and
you kind of just kind of wheel around
now the path is not always going to be
this corkscrew tile path it's actually
quite random you could kind of wobble
left and right but when I seeded it with
42 this is what it spread out so that's
what I'm using here you typically get
this corkscrew you get this cork scoring
for this set of parameters and yeah I
think this is a good explanation so some
combination of acceleration and noise
smoothing is why momentum works
oh yes yes so I should say that when we
inject noise here the gradient may not
even be the right direction to travel in
fact it could be in the opposite
direction from where you want to go and
this is why you kind of bounce around in
the valley there so in fact the gray you
can see here that the first step with
SUV is practically orthogonal to the
level set there that's because it is
such a good step at the beginning but
once you get further down it can point
in pretty much any direction vaguely
around the solution so yesterday with
momentum is currently state of the art
optimization method for a lot of machine
learning problems so you'll probably be
using it in your course for a lot of
problems but there has been some other
innovations over the years and these are
particularly useful for poorly
conditioned problems now as I mentioned
earlier in the lecture some problems
have this kind of well condition
property that we can't really
characterize for neural networks but we
can measure it by the test that if s to
D works then it's well conditioned
eventually there doesent works and if I
must be walking poorly conditioned so we
have other methods we can handle
we can use to handle this in some
situations and these generally are
called adaptive methods now you need to
be a little bit careful because what are
you adapting to people in literature use
this nomenclature for adapting learning
rates adapting momentum parameters but
in our our situation we're talk about a
specific type of adaptivity roman this
adaptivity is individual learning rates
now what I mean by that so in the
simulation I already showed you a
stochastic gradient descent
I used a global learning rate by that I
mean every single rate in your network
is updated using an equation with the
same gamma now gamma could vary over
time step so you used gamma K in the
notation but often you use a fixed
camera for quite a long time but for
adaptive methods we want to adapt a
learning rate for every weight
individually and we want to use
information we get from gradients for
each weight to adapt this so this seems
like the obvious thing to do and people
have been trying to get this stuff to
work for decades and we're kind of
stumbled upon some methods that work and
some that don't but I want to ask for
questions here if there's any any
explanation needed so I can say that
it's not entirely clear why you need to
do this right if your network is well
conditioned you don't need to do this
potentially but often the network's we
use in practice have very different
structure in different parts of the
network so for instance the early parts
of your convolutional neural network may
be very shallow convolutional layers on
large images later in the network you're
going to be doing convolutions with
large numbers of channels on small
images now these operations are very
different and there's no reason to
believe that a learning rate that works
well for one would work well for the
other and this is why the adaptive
learning rates can be useful any
questions here
yes so unfortunately there's no good
definition for neural networks we
couldn't measure it even if there was a
good definition so I'm going to use it
in a vague sense that it actually
doesn't works and it's poorly
conditioned
yes so in the sort of quadratic case if
you recall I have an explicit definition
of this condition number L over mu L
being maximized in value mu being
smallest eigen value and yeah the large
of this gap between largest larger and
smaller eigen value the worst condition
it is this does not imply if in your
network so that mu does not exist in
your networks L still has some
information in it but I wouldn't say
it's a determining factor there's just a
lot going on so there are some ways that
your looks behave a lot like simple
problems but there are other ways where
we just kind of hang wave and say that
they like them yeah yeah yes so for this
particular network this is a network
that actually isn't too poorly
conditioned already in fact this is a
VDD 16 which is practically the best net
method best network when you had a train
before the invention of certain
techniques to improve conditioning so
this is almost the best of first
condition you can actually get and there
are a lot of the structure of this
network is actually defined by this
conditioning like we double the number
of channels after certain steps because
that seems to result in networks at a
world condition rather than any other
reason but it's certainly what you can
say is that weights very light the
network have very large effect on the
output that very last layer there with
if there are 4096 weights in it that's a
very small number of whites this network
has millions of whites I believe those
4096 weights have a very strong effect
on the output because they directly
dictate that output and for that reason
you generally want to use smaller
learning rates for those whereas yeah
weights early in the network some of
them might have a large effect but
especially when you've initialized
network of randomly they typically will
have a smaller effect of those those
earlier weights and this is very hand
wavy and the reason why is because we
really don't understand this well enough
for me to give you a precise precise
statement here 120 million weights in
this network actually so yeah so that
last layer is like 4096 by 4096 matrix
so
yeah okay any other questions yeah yes I
would recommend only using them when
your problem doesn't have a structure
that decomposes into a large sum of
similar things okay yeah that's a bit of
a mouthful but sut works well when you
have an objective that is a sum where
each term of the sum is is vaguely
comparable so in machine learning each
sub term in this sum is a loss of one
data point and these have very similar
structures individual losses that's a
hand-wavy sense that they have very
similar structure because of course each
data point could be quite different but
when your problem doesn't have a large
sum as the main part of its structure
then l-bfgs would be useful that's the
general answer I doubt you make use of
it in this course l-bfgs doubt it that
it can be very handy for small networks
you can experiment around with it with
the leaner v network or something which
I'm sure you probably use in this course
you could experiment with l-bfgs
probably and have some success there one
of the kind of founding techniques in
modern your network training is rmsprop
and i'm going to talk about this year
now at some point kind of the standard
practice in the field of optimization is
in research and optimization kind of
diverged with what people were actually
doing when training neural networks and
this IMS prop was kind of the fracturing
point where we all went off in different
directions and this rmsprop is usually
attributed to Geoffrey Hinton slides
which he then attributes to an
unpublished paper from someone else
which is really unsatisfying to be
citing someone slides in a paper but
anyway it's a method that has some it
has no proof behind why it works but
it's similar to methods that you can
prove work so that's at least something
and it works pretty well in practice and
that's why I look if we use it so I want
to give you that kind of introduction
before what I explained what it actually
is and rmsprop
stands for root mean squared propagation
this was from the era where
everything we do the fuel networks we
called propagation such-and-such like
back prop which now we call deep so it
probably be called Armas deep propyl
something if it was embedded now and
it's a little bit of a modification so
it still to line algorithm but a little
bit different so I'm gonna go over these
terms in some detail because it's
important to understand this now we we
keep around this V buffer now this is
not a momentum buffer okay so we using
different notation here he is doing
something different and I'm going to use
some notation that that some people
really hates but I think it's convenient
I'm going to write the element wise
square of a vector just by squaring the
vector this is not really confusing
notationally in almost all situations
but it's a nice way to write it so here
I'm writing the gradient squared I
really mean you take every element in
that vector million element vector or
whatever it is and square each element
individually so this video update is
what's known as an exponential moving
average I do I have a quick show of
hands who's familiar with exponential
moving averages I want to know if I need
to talk about it in some more seems like
it's probably need to explain it in some
depth but in expose for a moving average
it's a standard way this has been used
for many many decades across many fields
for maintaining an average that are the
quantity that may change over time okay
so when a quantity is changing over time
we need to put larger weights on newer
values because they provide more
information and one way to do that is
down weight old values exponentially and
when you do this exponentially you mean
that the weight of an old value from say
ten steps ago will have weight alpha to
the ten in your thing so that's where
the exponential comes in the output of
the ten now it's that's not really in
the notation and in the notation at each
step we just download the pass vector by
this alpha constant and as if you can
imagine in your head things in that
buffer the V buffer that are very old at
each step they get downloaded by alpha
at every step and just as before alpha
here is something between zero and one
so we can't use values greater than one
there so this will damp those all values
until they no longer
the exponential moving average so this
method keeps an exponential moving
average of the second moment I mean
non-central second moment so we do not
subtract off the mean here the part or
implementation has a switch where you
can tell it to subtract off the mean
play with that if you like it'll
probably perform very similarly in
practice there's a paper on that I'm
sure but the original method does not
subtract off the mean there and we use
this second moment to normalize the
gradient and we do this element-wise so
all this notation is element wise every
element of the gradient is divided
through by the square root of the second
moment estimate and if you think that
this square root is really being the
standard deviation even though this is
not a central moment so it's not
actually the standard deviation it's
useful to think of it that way and the
name you know root means square is kind
of alluding to that division by the root
of the mean of the squares and the
important technical detail here you have
to add epsilon here for the annoying
problem that when you divide 0 by 0
everything breaks so you occasionally
have zeros in your network there are
some situations where it makes a
difference outside of when your
gradients zero but you absolutely do
need that epsilon in your method and
you'll see this is a recurring theme all
of these no adaptive methods basically
you've got to put an epsilon when your
the divide something just to avoiding to
avoid dividing by 0 and typically that
epsilon will be close to your machine
Epsilon I don't know if so if you're
familiar with that term but it's
something like 10 to a negative 7
sometimes 10 to the negative 8 something
of that order so really only has a small
effect on the value before I talk about
why this method works I want to talk
about the the most recent kind of
innovation on top of this method and
that is the method that we actually use
in practice so rmsprop is sometimes
still use but more often we use a method
notice atom an atom means adaptive
moment estimation so Adam is rmsprop
with momentum so I spent 20 minutes
telling you I should use momentum so I'm
going to say well you should put it on
top of rmsprop as well
there's always of doing that at least
half a dozen in this papers for each of
them but Adam is the one that caught on
and the way we do have a mention here is
we actually convert the momentum update
to an exponential moving average as well
now this may seem like a quantity
qualitatively different update like
doing momentum by moving average in fact
what we were doing before is essentially
equivalent to that you can work out some
constants where you can get a method
where you use a moving exponential
moving average momentum that is
equivalent to the regular mentum so
don't think of this moving average
momentum as being anything different
than your previous momentum but it has a
nice property that you don't need to
change the learning rate when you mess
with the beta here which I think it's a
big improvement so yeah we added
momentum of the gradient and just as
before with rmsprop we have this
exponential moving average of the
squared gradient on top of that we
basically just plug in this moving
average gradient where we had the
gradient in the previous update so it's
not too complicated now if you actually
read the atom paper you'll see a whole
bunch of additional notation the
algorithm is like ten lines long instead
of three and that is because they add
something called bias correction this is
actually not necessary but it'll help a
little bit so everybody uses it and all
it does is it increases the value of
these parameters during the early stages
of optimization and the reason you do
that is because you initialize this
momentum buffer at zero typically now
imagine your initial initializer at zero
then after the first step we're going to
be adding to that a value of 1 minus
beta times the gradient now 1 minus beta
will typically be 0.1 because we
typically use momentum point 9 so when
we do that our gradient step is actually
using a learning rate 10 times smaller
because this momentum buffer has a tenth
of a gradient in it
and that's undesirable so all the bias
correction does is just multiply by 10
the step in those early iterations and
the bias correction formula is just
basically the correct way to do that to
result in a step that's unbiased and
unbiased here means just the expectation
of the momentum buffer is the gradient
so it's nothing too mysterious
yeah don't think of it as being like a
huge addition although I do think that
the atom paper was the first one to use
bicycle action in a mainstream
optimization method I don't know if they
invented it but it certainly pioneered
the base correction so these methods
work really well in practice let me just
give you a common empirical comparison
here now this quadratic I'm using is a
diagonal quadratic so it's a little bit
shading to use a method that works well
on down or quadratics on and diagonal
quadratic but I'm gonna do that anyway
and you can see that the direction they
travel is quite an improvement over SGD
so in this simplified problem sut kind
of goes in the wrong direction at the
beginning where rmsprop basically heads
in the right direction now the problem
is rmsprop suffers from noise just as
regular sut without noise suffers so you
get this situation where kind of bounces
around the optimum quite significantly
and just as with std with momentum when
we add momentum to atom we get the same
kind of improvement where we kind of
corkscrew or sometimes reverse corkscrew
around the solution that kind of thing
and this gets you to the solution
quicker and it means that the last point
you're currently at is a good estimate
of the solution not a noisy estimate but
it's kind of the best estimate you have
so I would generally recommend using a
demova rmsprop and it's serving the case
that for some problems you just can't
use SGD atom is necessary for training
some of the neural networks were using
our language models or say our language
models it's necessary for training the
network so I'm going to talk about near
the end of this presentation and it's
it's generally the if I have to
recommend something you should use you
should try either s to D with momentum
or atom as you'll go to methods for
optimizing your networks so there's some
practical advice for you personally I
hate atom because I'm an optimization
researcher and the theory and their
paper is wrong this has been shown
recently so the method in fact does not
converge and you can show this on very
simple test problems so one of the most
heavily music
use methods in modern machine learning
actually doesn't work in a lot of
situations this is unsatisfying and it's
I'm kind of an ongoing research question
of the best way to fix this I don't
think just modifying Adam a little bit
to try and fix it is really the best
solution I think it's got some more
fundamental problems but I won't go into
any detail for that there is a very
practical problem they need to talk
about though Adam is known to sometimes
give worse generalization error I think
Yara's talked in detail about
generalization error do I go over that
so yeah generalization error is the
error on data that you didn't train your
model on basically so your networks are
very heavily parameter over
parameterised and if you train them to
give zero loss on the data you trained
it on they won't give zero loss on other
data points data that it's never seen
before and this generalization error is
that error typically the best thing we
can do is minimize the loss and the data
we have but sometimes that's suboptimal
and it turns out when you use Adam it's
quite common on particularly on image
problems that you get worst
generalization error than when you use
STD and people attribute this to a whole
bunch of different things it may be
finding those bad local minima that I
mentioned earlier the ones that are
smaller it's kind of unfortunate that
the better your optimization method the
more likely it is to hit those small
local minima because they're closer to
where you currently are and kind of it's
the goal of an optimization method to
find you the closest minima in a sense
these local optimization methods we use
but there's a whole bunch of other
reasons that you can attribute to it
less noise in Adam perhaps it could be
some structure
maybe these methods where you rescale
space like this have this fundamental
problem where they give worst
generalization we don't really
understand this but it's important to
know that this may be a problem or in
some cases it's not to say that it will
give horrible performance you'll still
get a pretty good neuron that workout at
the end and what I can tell you is the
language models that we trained at
Facebook use methods like atom or atom
itself and they
much better results than if you use STD
and there's a kind of a small thing that
won't affect you at all I would expect
but with Adam you have to maintain these
three buffers where's sed you have two
buffers of parameters this doesn't
matter except when you're training a
model that's like 12 gigabytes and then
it really becomes a problem I don't
think you'll encounter that in practice
and surely there's a little bit iffy so
you gotta trim two parameters instead of
one so yeah that's practical advice use
Adam arrest you do but onto something
that is also sup is also kind of a core
thing oh sorry have a question yes yes
you absolutely correct but typically I
guess the question the question was
weren't using a small epsilon in the
denominator result in blow-up certainly
if the numerator was equal to roughly
one than dividing through by ten to the
negative seven could be catastrophic and
this this is a legitimate question but
typically in order for the V buffer to
have very small values the gradient also
has to have had very small values you
can see that from the way the
exponential moving averages are updated
so in fact it's not a practical problem
when this when this V is incredibly
small the momentum is also very small
and when you're dividing small thing by
a small thing you don't get blow-up oh
yeah so the question is should I you buy
an SUV and atom separately at the same
time and just see which one works better
in fact that is pretty much what we do
because we have lots of computers we
just have one computer runners you need
one computer one atom and see which one
works better although we kind of know
from most problems which one is the
better choice for whatever problems
you're working with maybe you can try
both it depends how long it's going to
take to train I'm not sure exactly what
you're gonna be doing in terms of
practice in this course yeah certainly
legitimate way to do it
in fact some people use SGD at the
beginning and then switch to atom at the
end that's certainly a good approach it
just makes it more complicated and
complexity should be avoided if possible
yes this is one of those deep unanswered
questions so the question was should we
1s you deal with lots of different
initializations and see which one gets
the best solution won't I help with the
bumpiness
this is the case with small neural net
that you will get different solutions
depending on your initialization now
there's a remarkable property of the
kind of large networks we use at the
moment and the art networks as long as
you use similar random initialization in
terms of the variance of initialization
you'll end up practically at a similar
quality solutions and this is not well
understood so yeah it's it's quite
remarkable that your neural network can
train for three hundred epochs and you
end up with solution the test error is
like almost exactly the same as what you
got with some completely different
initialization we don't understand this
so if you really need to eke out tiny
performance gains you may be able to get
a little bit better Network by running
multiple and picking the best and it
seems the bigger your network and the
harder your problem the less game you
get from doing that yes so the question
was we have three buffers for each
weight on the answer answer is yes so
essentially yeah we basically in memory
we have a copy of the same size as our
weight data so our weight will be a
whole bunch of tensors in memory we have
a separate whole bunch of tensors that
our momentum tensors and we have a whole
bunch of other tensors that are the the
second moment tensors so yeah so
normalization layers so this is kind of
a clever idea why try and salt why try
and come up with a better optimization
algorithm where we can just come up with
a better network and this is the idea so
modern neural networks typically we
modify the network by adding additional
layers in between existing layers and
the goal of these layers to improve the
optimization and generalization
performance of the network and the way
they do this can happen in a few
different ways but let me give you an
example so we would typically take
standard kind of combinations so as you
know in modern your networks we
typically alternate linear operations
with nonlinear operations and here I
call that activation functions we
alternate them linear nonlinear linear
nonlinear what we could do is we can
place these normalization layers either
between the linear order non-linear or
before so there in this case we are
using for instance this is the kind of
structure we have in real networks where
we have a convolution recover that
convolutions or linear operations
followed by batch normalization this is
a type of normalization which I will
detail in a minute
followed by riilu which is currently the
most popular activation function and we
place this mobilization between these
existing layers and what I want to make
clear is this normalization layers they
affect the flow of data through so they
modify the data that's flowing through
but they don't change the power of the
network in the sense that that you can
set up the weights in the network in
some way that'll still give whatever
output you had in an unknown alized
network with a normalized network so
normalization layers you're not making
that work more powerful they improve it
in other ways normally when we add
things to a neural network the goal is
to make it more powerful and yes this
normalization layer can also be after
the activation or before the linear or
you know because this wraps around we do
this in order a lot of them are
equivalent but any questions here this
is this bits yes yes so that's certainly
true but we kind of want that we want
the real o2 sensor some of the data but
not too much but it's also not quite
accurate because normalization layers
can also scale and ship the data and so
it won't necessarily be that although
it's certainly at initialization they do
not do that scaling in ship so typically
cut off half the data and in fact if you
try to do a theoretical analysis of this
it's very convenient that it cuts off
half the data so the structure this
normalization layers they all pretty
much do the same kind of operation and
how many use kind of generic notation
here so you should imagine that X is an
input to the normalization layer and Y
is an output and what you do is use do a
whitening or normalization operation
where you subtract off some estimate of
the mean of the data and you divide
through by some estimate of the standard
deviation and remember before that I
mentioned we want to keep the
representational power of the network
the same
what we do to ensure that is we multiply
by an alpha and we add a sorry in height
multiplied by an hey and we add a B and
this is just so that the layer can still
output values over any particular range
or if we just always had every layer
output in white and data the network
couldn't output like a value million or
something like that it wouldn't it could
only do that you know with very in very
rare cases because that would be very
heavy on the tail of the normal
distribution so this allows our layers
to essentially output things that are
the same range as before and yes so
normalization layers have parameters and
in the network is a little bit more
complicated in the sensor has more
parameters it's typically a very small
number of parameters like rounding error
in your counts of network parameters
typically and yeah so the complexity of
this is on being kind of vague about how
you compute the mean and standard
deviation the reason I'm doing that is
because all the methods compute in a
different way and I'll detail that in a
second yes question weighs re lb oh it's
just a shift parameter so the data could
have had a nonzero mean and we want it
delayed to be able to produce outputs
with a nonzero mean so if we always just
subtract off the mean it couldn't do
that
so it just adds back representational
power to the layer yes so the question
is don't these a and B parameters
reverse the normalization and and in
fact that often is the case that they do
something similar but they move at
different time scales so between the
steps or between evaluations your
network the mean and variance can can
shift quite substantially based off the
data you're feeding but these a and B
parameters are quite stable they move
slowly as you learn them so because
they're most stable this has beneficial
properties and I'll describe those a
little bit later but I want to talk
about is exactly how you normalize the
data and this is where the crucial thing
so the earliest of these methods
developed was batch norm and he is this
kind of a bizarre normalization that I I
think is a horrible idea
but unfortunately works fantastically
well so it normalizes across batches so
we want information about a certain
channel recall for a convolutional
neural network which channel is one of
these latent images that you have in
your network that part way through the
network you have some data it doesn't
really look like an image if you
actually look at it but it's it's shaped
like an image anyway and that's a
channel so we want to compute an average
over this over this channel but we only
have a small amount of data that's
what's in this channel basically height
times width if it's a if it's an image
and it turns out that's not enough data
to get good estimates of these mean and
variance parameters so what batchman
does is it takes a mean and variance
estimate across all the instances in
your mini-batch pretty straightforward
and that's what it divides blue by the
reason why I don't like this is it is no
longer actually stochastic gradient
descent if you using batch normalization
so it breaks all the theory that I work
on for a living so I prefer some other
normalization strategies there in fact
quite a soon after Bachelor and people
tried normalizing via every other
possible combination of things you can
normalize by and it turns out the three
that kind of work a layer instance and
group norm and layer norm here in this
diagram you averaged across all of the
channels and across height and width now
this doesn't work on all problems so I
would only recommend it on a problem
where you know it already works and
that's typically a problem where people
already using it so look at what the
network's people are using if that's a
good idea or not will depend the
instance normalization is something
that's used a lot in modern language
models and this you do not average
across the batch anymore which is nice I
won't we talk about that much depth I
really the one I would rather you rather
you use in practice is group
normalization so here we have which
across a group of channels and this
group is trapped is chosen arbitrarily
and fixed at the beginning so typically
we just group things numerically so
channel 0 to 10
would be a group channel you know 10 to
20 making sure you don't overlap of
course disjoint groups of channels and
the size of these groups is a parameter
that you need to tune although we always
use 32 in practice you could tune that
and you just do this because there's not
enough information on a single channel
and using all the channels is too much
so you just use something in between
it's it's really quite a simple idea and
it turns out this group norm often works
better than batch normal a lot of
problems and it does mean that my HUD
theory that I work on is still balanced
so I like that
so why does normalization help this is a
matter of dispute so in fact in the last
few years several papers have come out
on this topic
unfortunately the papers did not agree
on why it works they all have completely
separate explanations but there's some
things that are definitely going on
so we can shape it we can say for sure
that the network appears to be easier to
optimize so by that I mean you can use
large learning rates better in a better
condition network you can use larger
learning rates and therefore get faster
convergence so that does seem to be the
case when you uses normalization layers
another factor which is a little bit
disputed but I think is reasonably
well-established
you get noise in the data passing
through your network when you use
normalization in vaginal and this noise
comes from other instances in the bash
because it's random what I like
instances are in your batch when you
compute the mean using those other
instances that mean is noisy and this
noise is then added or sorry subtracted
from your weight so when you do the
normalization operation so this noise is
actually potentially helping
generalization performance in your
network now there has been a lot of
papers on injecting noise internet works
to help generalization so it's not such
a crazy idea that this noise can be
helping and in terms of a practical
consideration this normalization makes
the weight initialization that you use a
lot less important it used to be kind of
a black art to select the initialization
your new your network and the people who
really good motive is often it was just
because they're really good at changing
their initialization and this is just
less the case now when we use
normalization layers and also gives the
benefit if you can kind of tile together
layers with impunity so again it used to
be the situation that if you just plug
together two possible ways in your
network it probably wouldn't work now
that we use normalization layers it
probably will work and even if it's a
horrible idea and this has spurred a
whole field of automated architecture
search where they just randomly calm
build together blocks and it's try
thousands of them and see what works and
that really wasn't possible before
because that would typically result in a
poorly conditioned Network you couldn't
train and with normalization typically
you can train it some practical
considerations so the the bachelor on
paper one of the reasons why it wasn't
invented earlier is the kind of
non-obvious thing that you have to back
propagate through the calculation of the
mean and standard deviation if you don't
do this everything blows up now you
might have to do this yourself as it'll
be implemented in the implementation
that you use oh yes so I do not have the
expertise to answer that I feel like
it's kind of sometimes it's just a
patent pet method like people like
layering in suits normally that field
more and in fact a good norm if you it's
just the group size covers both so I
would be sure that you could probably
get the same performance using group
norm with a particular group size chosen
carefully
yeah the choice of national does affect
parallelization so the implementation
zinc in your computer library or your
CPU library are pretty efficient for
each of these but it's complicated when
you are spreading your computation
across machines and you kind of have to
synchronize these these these things and
batch norm is a bit of a pain there
because it would mean that you need to
compute an average across all machines
and aggregator whereas if you're using
group norm every instance is on a
different machine you can just
completely compute the norm so in all
those other three it's separate
normalization for each instance it
doesn't depend on the other instances in
the batch so it's nicer when you're
distributing it's
when people use batch norm on a cluster
they actually do not sync the statistics
across which makes it even less like SGD
and makes me even more annoyed so what
was it already
yes yeah Bachelor basically has a lot of
momentum not in the optimization sense
but in the sense of people's minds so
it's very heavily used for that reason
but I would recommend group norm instead
and there's kind of like a technical
data with batch norm you don't want to
compute these mean and standard
deviations on batches during evaluation
time by evaluation time I mean when you
actually run your network on the test
data set or we use it in the real world
for some application it's typically in
those situations you don't have batches
any more batches or more for training
things so you need some substitution in
that case you can compute an exponential
moving average as we talked about before
and EMA of these mean and standard
deviations you may think to yourself why
don't we use an EMA in the
implementation of batch norm the answer
is because it doesn't work we it seems
like a very reasonable idea though and
people have explored that and quite a
lot of depth but it doesn't work oh yes
this is quite crucial so yet people have
tried normalizing things in neural
networks before a batch norm was
invented but they always made the
mistake of not back popping through the
mean and standard deviation and the
reason why they didn't do that is
because the math is really tricky and if
you try to implement it yourself it will
probably be wrong now that we have pie
charts which which computes gradients
correctly for you in all situations you
could actually do this in practice and
there are just a little bit but only a
little bit because it's surprisingly
difficult yeah so the question is is
there a difference if we apply
normalization before after than
non-linearity and the answer is there
will be a small difference in the
performance of your network now I can't
tell you which one's better because it
appears in some situation one works a
little bit better in other situations
the other one works better what I can
tell you is the way I draw it here is
what's used in the PI project
implementation of ResNet and most
resonant implementations so just there's
probably almost as good as you can get I
think that would use the other form if
it was better and it's certainly problem
depended this is another one of those
things where maybe the
no correct answer how you do it and it's
just random which works better I don't
know yes yeah any other questions on
this before I move on to the so you need
more data to get accurate estimates of
the mean and standard deviation the
question was why is it a good idea to
compute it across multiple channels
rather than a single channel and yes it
is because you just have more data to
make a better estimates but you want to
be careful you don't have too much data
in that because then you don't get the
noise and record that the noise is
actually useful so basically the group
size in group norm is just adjusting the
amount of noise we have basically the
question was how is this related to
group convolutions this was all
pioneered before good convolutions were
used it certainly has some interaction
with group convolutions if you use them
and so you want to be a little bit
careful there I don't know exactly what
the correct thing to do is in those
cases but I can tell you they definitely
use normalization in those situations
probably Batchelor more more than group
norm because of the momentum I mentioned
it's just more popular vaginal yes so
the question is do we ever use our Beck
instances from the mini-batch in group
norm or is it always just a single
instance we always just use a single
instance because there's so many
benefits to that it's so much simpler in
implementation and in theory to do that
maybe you can get some improvement from
that in fact I bet you there's a paper
that does that somewhere because they've
tried have any combination of this in
practice I suspect if it worked well
we'd probably be using it so probably
probably doesn't work well under the the
death of optimization I wanted to put
something a little bit interesting
because you've all been sitting through
kind of a pretty dense lecture so this
is something that I've kind of been
working on a little bit I thought you
might find interesting so you might have
seen the the xkcd comic here that I've
modified it's not always this way it's
kind of point of what it makes so
sometimes we can just barge into a field
we know nothing about it and improve on
how they're currently doing it although
you have to be a little bit careful so
the problem I want to talk about is one
that young I think mentioned briefly in
the first lecture but I want to go into
a bit of detail it's MRI reconstruction
now in the MRI reconstruction problem
we take a raw data from an MRI machine a
medical imaging machine we take raw data
from that machine and we reconstruct an
image and there's some pipeline an
algorithm in the middle there that
produces the image and the goal
basically here is to replace 30 years of
research into what algorithm they should
use their with with neural networks
because that's that's what I'll get paid
to do and I'll give you a bit of detail
so these MRI machines capture data in
what's known as the Fourier domain I
know a lot of you have done signal
processing some of you may have no idea
what this is and you don't need to
understand it for this problem oh yeah
yes so you may have seen the the further
domain in one dimensional case
so for neural networks sorry for MRI
reconstruction we have two dimensional
Fourier domain the thing you need to
know is it's a linear mapping to get
from the fluid domain to image domain
it's just linear and it's very efficient
to do that mapping it literally takes
milliseconds no matter how big your
images on modern computers so linear and
easy to convert back and forth between
the two and the MRI machines actually
capture either rows or columns of this
Fourier domain as samples they're called
sample in the literature so each time
the machine computes a sample which is
every few milliseconds it gets a role
column of this image and this is
actually technically a complex-valued
image but this does not matter for my
discussion of it so you can imagine it's
just a two channel image if you imagine
a real and imaginary channel just think
of them as color channels the problem we
want to do we want to solve is
accelerating MRI acceleration here is in
the sense of faster so we want to run
the machines quicker and produce
identical quality images
and one way we can do that in the most
successful way so far is by just not
capturing all of the columns we just
skip some randomly it's useful in
practice to also capture some of the
middle columns it turns out they contain
a lot of the information but outside the
middle we just capture randomly and we
can't just use a nice linear operation
anymore
that diagram on the right is the output
of that linear operation I mentioned
applied to this data so it doesn't give
useful Apple they only do something a
little bit more intelligent any
questions on this before I move on
it is frequency and phase dimensions so
in this particular case I'm actually
sure this diagram one of the dimensions
is frequency and one is phase and the
value is the magnitude of a sine wave
with that frequency and phase so if you
add together all the sine waves wave
them with the frequency oh so with the
weight in this image you get the
original image so it's it's a little bit
more complicated because it's in two
dimensions and the sine waves you gotta
be little bit careful but it's basically
just each pixel is the magnitude of a
sine wave or if you want to compare to a
1d analogy
you'll just have frequencies so the
pixel intensity is the strength of that
frequency if you have a musical note say
a piano note with a C major as one of
the frequencies that would be one pixel
this image would be the C major
frequency and another might be a minor
or something like that and the magnitude
of it is just how hard they press the
key on the piano so you have frequency
information yes so the video doesn't
work there was one of the biggest
breakthroughs in in Threat achill
mathematics for a long time was the
invention of compressed sensing I'm sure
some of you have heard of compressed
sensing a hands of show of hands
compressed sensing yeah some of you
especially work in the mathematical
sciences would be aware of it
basically there's this phenomenal
political paper that showed that we
could actually in theory get a perfect
reconstruction from these subsampled
measurements and we had some
requirements for this to work the
requirements were that we needed to
sample randomly
in fact it's a bit weaker you have to
sample incoherently but in practice
everybody samples randomly so it's
essentially the same thing now here
we're randomly sampling columns but
within the columns we do not randomly
sample the reason being is it's not
faster in the machine the machine can
capture one column as quickly as you
could capture half a column so we just
kind of capture a whole column so that
makes it no longer random so that's one
kind of problem with it the other
problem is kind of the the assumptions
of this compressed sensing theory are
violated by the kind of images we want
to reconstruct I show you on the right
they're an example of compressed sensing
Theory reconstruction this was a big
step forward from what they could do
before you would you'll get something
that looks like this previously that was
really considered the best in fact some
people would when this result came out
swore though this was impossible it's
actually not but you need some
assumptions and these assumptions are
pretty critical and I mention them there
so you need sparsity of the image now
that mi a-- majors not sparse by sparse
I mean it has a lot of zero or black
pixels it's clearly not sparse but it
can be represented sparsely or
approximately sparsely if you do a
wavelet decomposition now I won't go to
the details there's a little bit of
problem though it's only approximately
sparse and when you do that wavelet
decomposition that's why this is not a
perfect reconstruction if it was very
sparse in the wavelet domain and
perfectly that would be in exactly the
same as the left image and this
compressed sensing is based off of the
field of optimization it kind of
revitalize a lot of the techniques
people have been using for a long time
the way you get this reconstruction is
you solve a little mini optimization
problem at every step you every image
you want to reconstruct how many other
machines so your machine has to solve an
optimization problem for every image
every time it solves this little
quadratic problem with this kind of
complicated regularization term so this
is great for optimization or all these
people who had been getting low paid
jobs at universities all of a sudden
there of their research was trendy and
corporations needed their help so this
is great but we can do better so we
instead of solving this minimization
problem at every time step I will use a
neural network so obviously being here
arbitrarily to represent the huge in
your network beef a big of course we we
hope that we can learn in your network
of such sufficient complexity that it
can essentially solve the optimization
problem in one step it just outputs a
solution that's as good as the
optimization problem solution now this
would have been considered impossible 15
years ago now we know better so it's
actually not very difficult in fact we
can just take an example of we can solve
a few of these a few I mean like a few
hundred thousand of these optimization
problems take the solution and the input
and we're gonna strain a neural network
to map from input to solution that's
actually a little bit suboptimal because
we get weakened in some cases we know a
better solution than the solution to the
optimization problem we can gather that
by measuring the patient and that's what
we actually do in practice so we don't
try and solve the optimization problem
we try and get to an even better
solution and this works really well so
I'll give you a very simple example of
this so this is what you can do much
better than the compressed sensory
reconstruction using a neural network
and this network involves the tricks
I've mentioned so it's trained using
Adam it uses group norm normalization
layers and convolutional neural networks
as you've already been taught and it
uses a technique known as u nets which
you may go over later in the course not
sure about that but it's not a very
complicated modification of only one it
works as yeah this is the kind of thing
you can do and this is this is very
close to practical applications so
you'll be seeing these accelerated MRI
scans happening in in clinical practice
in only a few years tired this is not
vaporware and yeah that's everything i
wanted to talk about you talk about
today optimization and the death of
optimization thank you